<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="index" lang="C">
  <articleinfo>
    <title><application>Déjà Dup</application> Manual</title>
    <abstract role="description">
      <para><application>Déjà Dup</application> is a simple backup tool.</para>
    </abstract>

    <publisher role="maintainer">
      <publishername><ulink url="http://launchpad.net/~deja-dup-team" type="http"><application>Déjà Dup</application> Administrators</ulink></publishername>
    </publisher>
    
    <legalnotice id="legalnotice">
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU General Public License (GPL), Version 3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation.  You can find a copy of the GPL at this <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gpl">link</ulink> or in the file COPYING distributed with this manual.</para>
      <para>This manual is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU General Public License for more details.</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Michael</firstname>
        <surname>Terry</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <address> <email>mike@mterry.name</email> </address>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>%VERSION%</revnumber>
        <date>%DATE%</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para role="author">Michael Terry <email>mike@mterry.name</email></para>
          <para role="publisher"><ulink url="http://launchpad.net/~deja-dup-team" type="http"><application>Déjà Dup</application> Administrators</ulink></para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

    <releaseinfo>This manual describes version %VERSION% of Déjà Dup.</releaseinfo>
    <legalnotice>
      <title>Feedback</title>
      <para>To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding the <application>Déjà Dup</application> application or this manual, visit the <ulink url="http://bugs.launchpad.net/deja-dup" type="http"><application>Déjà Dup</application> project page</ulink>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <indexterm zone="index">
    <primary>Déjà Dup</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm zone="index">
    <primary>deja-dup</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect1 id="deja-dup-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para><application>Déjà Dup</application> is a simple backup program. It hides the complexity of doing backups the 'right way' (encrypted, off-site, and regular) and uses duplicity as the backend. </para>
    <para><application>Déjà Dup</application> provides the following features:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Support for local or remote backup locations, including Amazon S3</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Securely encrypts and compresses your data.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Incrementally backs up, letting you restore from any particular backup.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Schedules regular backups.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Integrates well into your GNOME desktop.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="deja-dup-getting-started">
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <sect2 id="deja-dup-start">
      <title>Starting <application>Déjà Dup</application></title>
      <para>You can start <application>Déjà Dup</application> in the following ways:</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Accessories</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Déjà Dup Backup Tool</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Command line</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>To start <application>Déjà Dup</application> from a command line, type the following command, then press <keycap>Return</keycap>:</para>
            <para><command>deja-dup</command></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="deja-dup-backup">
    <title>Backing Up</title>
    <para>To backup, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Backup</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Or press the <guibutton>Backup</guibutton> button on the main window.</para>
    <para>The <guilabel>Backup</guilabel> dialog will then be displayed.  If this is your first time using <application>Déjà Dup</application>, you will be asked to choose a backup location and which files to include or exclude.  On the Summary page, click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to start the backup.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="deja-dup-restore">
    <title>Restoring</title>
    <para>To restore, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Restore</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Or press the <guibutton>Restore</guibutton> button on the main window.</para>
    <para>The <guilabel>Restore</guilabel> dialog will then be displayed.  If this is your first time using <application>Déjà Dup</application>, you will be asked to choose a backup location.  Then choose which backup date to restore from and where to put the restored files. You can either restore them to their original locations or put them under a folder of your choice.</para>
    <para>After clicking <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>, you can review your restore options, then click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to start the restore.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="deja-dup-prefs">
    <title>Preferences</title>
    <para>To configure <application>Déjà Dup</application>, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Backup location</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use this drop-down list box to specify the backup location that <application>Déjà Dup</application> uses when backing up or restoring:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Amazon S3</guilabel></para>
              <para>This backup location uses the S3 storage service from Amazon. For a small fee per gigabyte, they hold your data for you. This is the recommended default because it is an easy way to keep your data offsite (meaning out of your home: in case of disaster or theft, your data will still be safe). You can sign up <ulink url="http://aws.amazon.com/s3/" type="http">online</ulink>.</para>
              <caution><para>This service costs money.  Read their rates carefully before using it.</para></caution>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Removable Media</para>
              <para>You may see removable media like external hard drives or thumb drives listed.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Connected Servers</para>
              <para>If you have connected to any servers, they will appear.  To connect to a server not listed, select <guilabel>Other...</guilabel> and click <guibutton>Connect to Server...</guibutton>.  This will let you enter the server information.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Local Folders</para>
              <para>You may also want to choose a local folder as a backup location.  Note that backups can be quite large, so make sure you have enough free disk space.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>Default: <guilabel>Amazon S3</guilabel>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>S3 Access Key ID</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <note><para>This option only appears if the <guilabel>Amazon S3</guilabel>
        backup location has been selected.</para></note>
          <para>This is your Access Key ID that Amazon gave you when you signed up for S3. It is like a username for logging into S3. If left empty, you will be prompted for it as you backup or restore.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Folder</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <note><para>This option only appears if the <guilabel>Amazon S3</guilabel> backup location has been selected.</para></note>
          <para>If you have multiple backups, you may want to keep them separated in multiple folders.  Use this option to enter a path on the S3 service in which to put your files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Include files in folders</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select a list of directories to backup. Press the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> or <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> buttons to modify the list. If you are only interested in backing up your own data, the default of <guilabel>Home Folder</guilabel> is sufficient.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Except files in folders</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select a list of directories to not backup. Press the <guibutton>Add </guibutton> or <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> buttons to modify the list. This list takes precedence over the list of included directories.</para>
          <para>Some of your data may be large and not very important to you.  In that case, you can save yourself some time and space by not backing them up.</para>
          <para>There are some locations that <application>Déjà Dup</application> excludes by default:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>~/.cache</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>~/.thumbnails</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>~/.gvfs</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>~/.xsession-errors</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>~/.recently-used.xbel</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>~/.recent-applications.xbel</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>~/.Private</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>/proc</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>/tmp</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>/sys</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Encrypt backup files</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Encrypting your backup files is recommended to keep your data safe. If you don't have exclusive physical control of your backup location, or if it is stolen, an encrypted backup prevents others from looking at your personal data.</para>
          <para>If on, you will be prompted for a password. Keep this password safe, you will need it to restore your data.</para>
          <para>Default: <userinput>On</userinput>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Automatically backup on a regular schedule</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Turn this option on to have <application>Déjà Dup</application> automatically backup for you. This is recommended so that you don't forget to backup. Backups are more useful the more recently you have made them, so it is important to regularly do so.</para>
          <para>Default: <userinput>Off</userinput>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>How often to backup</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose a schedule for automatic backups.</para>
          <para>Default: <guilabel>Weekly</guilabel>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
</article>
